<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A plain sermon preached to a country congregation in the beginning of the late rebellion in the west published for the instruction of country people in their duty to the King, and the refutation of some slanderous reports raised upon the preacher / by Vin. Owen.</title>
            <author>Owen, Vin.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 58 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53752</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing O832A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20886</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12610785</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12610785</idno>
            <idno type="VID">64363</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53752)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64363)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 771:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A plain sermon preached to a country congregation in the beginning of the late rebellion in the west published for the instruction of country people in their duty to the King, and the refutation of some slanderous reports raised upon the preacher / by Vin. Owen.</title>
                  <author>Owen, Vin.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 27 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed, and sold by Randolph Taylor ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Romans XIII, 1 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:64363:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64363:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Plain SERMON Preached to a <hi>Country Congregation</hi> In the beginning of the late REBELLION IN THE WEST.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed for the Inſtruction of Country People in their Duty to the King, and the Refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of ſome ſlanderous Reports raiſed upon the Preacher.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Vin. Owen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed, and Sold, by <hi>Randolph Taylor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="6 letters">
                     <desc>••••••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ners-Hall.</hi> 1685.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:64363:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64363:2"/>
            <head>AN ADVERTISEMENT TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THis plain Sermon Preached to a Countrey Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, without any deſign of making it pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lic, was drawn from me by the Clamors of ſome People againſt it, and the Aſperſions they caſt upon me for it. The Occaſion of Preaching it was this; when I firſt heard the news of the late Rebels in the Weſt, I thought it my Duty to put my Pariſhioners in mind of their Duty to the King, and to endeavour to confirm them in their Loyalty againſt all ſuch Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as they might (probably) meet with from evil mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men. To that end, I preached the greateſt part of what is here Printed the next Lords day, hoping that it might do good, and being Confident that it would not give the leaſt offence, becauſe I had more then once up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſome Occaſion or other, either in Preaching or Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſing, delivered the ſame things for ſubſtance, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended no body by it. But within two days after, I was
<pb facs="tcp:64363:3"/>told that ſome of my Pariſhoners had ſaid. I had made a bad Sermon the Sunday before, a Sermon that had lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of the Goſpel in it; but why they thought ſo or what they faulted, or who thoſe wiſe men were, I could not learn from him that told it me: And the next day there was a Report brought to my Houſe, from a Village ſeven miles diſtant, That I had Preached the beſt and greateſt part of my Pariſhoners out of the Church. This great lye I could not but wonder at, and being told that it was one of my own Pariſh that brought it thither, and had (probably) carried it further, it was ſome trouble to me. And upon ſecond thought I reſolved to Preach the ſame Sermon again (as near as I could in the very ſame words) the next Lords day, preſuming that ſome of the more ignorant ſort of People had miſunderſtood my words, or that there was great need of inculating the ſame things to prevent (if it were poſſible) the riſing of any Seditious or Rebellious thoughts in any of them, or to ſuppreſs them, if they were already riſin, which ſome Storys that were ſcattered abrord the Countrey, and were but to eaſily believed by the common ſort, did make me afraid of. Accordingly I did ſo, adding in the cloſe ſome few things upon the ſame Subject. But before that work was ended, I was informd that I was become the talk of the County, and inquiring upon what account, I heard it was for preaching Popery; and it was ſaid by many, that I was turning Papiſt, if not turned; and it was added that I had great Correſpondence with a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman of the Popiſh Religion in my Pariſh, ſent him News and received News from him dayly (though I had not ſeen nor heard from him in ſeveral Months, and he was at that time (as I was informed) in <hi>Warwick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire</hi>) and it was ſaid in a Popiſh houſe not three-miles
<pb facs="tcp:64363:3"/>from me, That I had Preach'd that the Pope was Supream Head of the Church. How I reſented theſe ſlanderous Storys, the Reader may eaſily gueſs. That in a Pariſh where I had lived ſeveral years, and taken no little pains, Preaching and Catechiſing Conſtantly every Lords day, and ſometimes on other days; when I had wronged none but obliged all ſo far as in me lay; where I had not been exact in requiring my dues, nor vexed any with Law Suits, how obnoctious ſoever they were to them; where I had ſpent almoſt all I had received in Hoſpitality and Charity; where I had forgiven many wrongs, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſo paſt them by, as not once to mention them to thoſe that did them, leaving them wholly to the Reproofs of their on Conſciences; and it ſhort where I deſerved not the leaſt ill will (as many will bear me witneſs) for which I muſt for ever glory to God, and I ſpeak it not out of a humor of boaſting, but as conſtrained to it, to convince my ſlanderers of the greatneſs of their ſin; That in ſuch a Pariſh (I ſay) I ſhould find any ſo blockiſhly ignorant in matters of Religion, ſo heedlſs and inconſiderate as to call that Popery which was downright againſt it; or ſo ill affected towards me as to raiſe and ſpread a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad ſuch ſlanderous Reports againſt me, at ſuch a time, and when they could not but know, that if the Rebels had been able to have brought their forces amongſt us, the Reports would have expoſed me to their Fury, and in all probability have coſt me my life, if they could have got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten me into their Hands; or that they ſhould be ſo ill affected towards the King (when I am ſure they had been taught better) as for his ſake to Perſecute me thus with their Tongues, all this I belive the Readerr will think was no light Affliction to me. And yet this was not all, for as I had reaſon to believe that I had loſt all my
<pb facs="tcp:64363:4"/>
               <hi>labour of Love</hi> with many of them, and ſaw them in the ready way to loſe their own Souls; ſo by what I heard from ſome of my Reverend Brethren concerning the Carriage of the people towards them, I ſaw plainly that the Enemies of our Religion would draw no ſmall Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage from thier Humor and Doings, and that they were taking a direct Courſe to deprive themſelves of that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion they ſeem ſo fond of. But how ſadly ſoever I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented all this, and more then this, I reſolved to keep my Reſentments to my ſelf, and never to declare them to any; and had done ſo, I beileve, if it had not come into my thoughts, that my ſeeming unconcernedneſs might be interpreted to my prejudice, and made an Argument againſt me that I was indeed very much inclined towards Popery. Having therefore changed my Reſolution, and begun to unboſom to my ſelf to ſome of my Friends, they told not that the best, if not the only way (the Report being carried ſo far) to wipe of thoſe Aſperſions, and to make the ſlanderers aſhamed, was to Print my Sermon. This Advice (though not approved at firſt) I reſolved at length to follow, upon theſe Confederations; That I was concerned to wipe them of, if I deſired to do any good in the Countrey, the name of a Papiſt being no leſs hated by the generality then that of the Devil, and becoming every day more odious to them by the Storys that go about (with how much truth I know not) of the threatning Speeches and inſolent Actions of ſome of them. That the Sermon, plain at it is, contains wholſom inſtructions, and may do ſome good, with Gods bleſſing, both among <hi>Proteſtants</hi> and <hi>Papiſts;</hi> for that ſome of both ſorts will read it, who have read nothing elſe upon this Subject, I am very Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident. That ſome who are too apt to ſlander the Clergy may be reſtrained in ſome meaſure from it by what is
<pb facs="tcp:64363:4"/>here accounted for, and others may become leſs forward to entertain any ill ſtoryes that are raiſed concerning them. Theſe and ſome other Reaſons induced me to publiſh it, and to put my Name to it, though I had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly reſolved that my Name ſhould never be put to any book. I have only one thing more to ſay as to this matter, <hi>viz.</hi> That I have Printed nothing but what I Preached, from the beginning to the end of the third par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular concerning the Perſons commanded to be ſubject; and have left out nothing material, only ſome words here and there which I uſed in ſpeaking to explain my mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and make it more eaſy to be understood by ignorant people; and that the cloſe is a little of another <hi>Sermon</hi> Preached afterwards upon the latter part of the verſe, for I continued to preach upon the ſame Subject, till the news came that the Rebels were vanquiſhed,</p>
            <p>And now if this fall into the Hands of any of my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Brethren of the Clergy, I would deſire them to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider with me how much we are concern'd to <hi>take heed to our ſelves, and to our Doctrine,</hi> in theſe Times; to Arme our ſelves with Courage against all the ill <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſage we are like to meet with, both from thoſe who are yet our own people, and from thoſe that are not; to unite all together in Love, to defend againſt all adverſaryes our Common Intereſt, I mean not our ſmall Revenues, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations and the like, though theſe are not to be ſlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but I mean our moſt <hi>Holy Religion,</hi> and the Laws of that beſt of Churches to which we do belong, to implore Gods mercy dayly towards our People, and beg Pardon from him for their Abuſe of the Goſpel, and their vile treating of us its unworthy Miniſters: And earneſtly to beſeech him to kindle and maintain in our hearts ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:64363:5"/>a fervent Love to their Souls, which Chriſt has redeemed with his moſt precious blood, that no diſcouragement we may receive from any may be of force to render us careleſs of them, and make us ceaſe to labour with all our might for their everlaſting Salvation. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From</hi> Mounſtow <date>
                     <hi>the</hi> 20th. of July <hi>1685.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:64363:5"/>
            <head>A Plain SERMON Preached to a Country Congregation In the beginning of the late REBELLION IN THE WEST, &amp;c.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Rom. 13. verſ. 1.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>Let every Soul be Subject unto the Higher Powers.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THat you may underſtand theſe Words, and your own Duty, I muſt deſire you to Conſider with me three things, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. What is here meant by the <hi>Higher Powers.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. What it is <hi>to be Subject</hi> unto them.</item>
               <item>3. What is meant by <hi>every Soul.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. What is here meant by the <hi>Higher Powers.</hi> And for the better underſtanding of this, and that I may take occaſion to ſuggeſt ſome things to you, which are but too needful to be ſuggeſted in theſe
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:64363:6"/>days, I muſt deſire you to note the following Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By the <hi>Higher Powers</hi> we muſt underſtand <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Earthly Powers.</hi> Such as are <hi>ordained of God</hi> for the Government of the World, and under God, take care of the Publick weal, being his Miniſters, to encourage and reward thoſe that do good, and to puniſh thoſe that do evil; to whom <hi>Tribute</hi> is therefore to be paid, as a juſt Acknowledgment of their Care and Pains for the Common good.</p>
            <p>This is ſo plain from the words of the Text, and thoſe that follow them, that I need not inſiſt upon it. But this I have noted, to diſcover to you the folly and wickedneſs of thoſe, that oppoſe <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> or <hi>Magiſtracy,</hi> as contrary to the Goſpel, and as an Uſurpation upon Chriſtian Liberty. That there were ſuch People in the very firſt Times of Chriſtianity, is evident from what the Apoſtle St. <hi>Peter</hi> in his ſecond Epiſtle, <hi>Chap.</hi> 2. <hi>verſ.</hi> 10. and the Apoſtle St. <hi>Jude</hi> verſ. 8. of his Epiſtle, do tell us. Where we read of <hi>Filthy Dreamers, that defiled the Fleſh, living in the Luſt of uncleaneſs, and deſpiſed Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion</hi> [or Government] <hi>and ſpeak evil of Dignitys:</hi> pretending (as we may probaly gather from other places of Holy Scripture) that the Goſpel freed them from all obligation to Magiſtrates, as ſuch, and that they were not bound to be ſubject to them. That theſe men were of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and of the <hi>Sect</hi> of the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> before their taking upon them the Profeſſion of Chriſtianity, I cannot affirm; but it is probable that they were, for 'tis certain that the <hi>Phariſees</hi> were a proud and ungovernable ſort of People, ſo Pure and Holy, and ſo dear to God in in their own conceit, that they thought it unfit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:64363:6"/>for them to be Subject, or to pay Tribute to the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperors; And therefore as they did ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral times Rebel, for they did always watch for op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities to caſt off the <hi>Roman</hi> Yoke. And it is certain that as the <hi>Phariſees</hi> looked upon themſelves to be Gods peculiar People, and as ſuch were not to acknowledge any Power over them, but that of God, as only King and Ruler of his People; ſo theſe filthy <hi>Heretics</hi> pretending themſelves to be the choſen People of God, would own no King or Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler over them, but Chriſt, and as they were his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants and Subjects, they were a free People as to all other <hi>Powers;</hi> But however this may be, the Apoſtles of our Lord eſteemed their Doctrine ſo deſtructive to the peace and welfare of human Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, and ſo ſcandalous to the Chriſtian Profeſſion, that they thought they could not too often caution Chriſtians againſt it, or beſtow too black a Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter upon them that taught it. And yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all the cautions they have given us in their Epiſtles, and the many hard things they have written of them, we know that there have been many ſuch People of late years in this Kingdom, that will acknowledg no King over them but Chriſt, and own no Government but what they call his, would be all Powers themſelves, and next to Chriſt, at his <hi>Right hand</hi> or <hi>Left hand.</hi> They account themſelves ſo perfect, that they eſteem all <hi>Human Powers</hi> as needleſs, though all men ſee, that they have not the leaſt ſpark of that Perfection they do boaſt of, and have as much need of Government, as the <hi>Horſe and Mule of a Bit and Bridle.</hi> They cry up Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Liberty, and would make the World believe that Subjection to <hi>Human Powers</hi> is contrary to it:
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:64363:7"/>but the Liberty they cry up is nothing elſe but a <hi>Cloak</hi> for their <hi>Naughtineſs</hi> (or maliciouſneſs) and a pretence for them <hi>to do what is good in their own Eyes;</hi> and you need not be remembered, that when there <hi>was no King in Iſrael,</hi> and every man did ſo, there was nothing but Outrage and Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenee and Confuſion both among them and us. In ſhort, the Liberty they talk of is ſo far from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſtian Liberty, that it is Antichriſtian Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſneſs, Rudeneſs, and Licentiouſneſs; for Chriſt hath taught us Subjection to the <hi>Higher Powers,</hi> and hath, aſſured us by his Apoſtle here, <hi>that there is no Power but of God, and the Powers that be, are ordained of God.</hi> And therefore if we be truly Chriſts Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, we ſhall be as truly the Kings Subjects, and faithfully perform the Dutys of ſuch, becauſe Chriſt hath ſo commanded us.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By the <hi>Higher Powers</hi> you are not to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand any thing diſtinct from the Perſons in Power, but the Perſons in Power themſelves. This is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent from the Context; for the <hi>Higher Powers</hi> in the Text are no other then the <hi>Ruders</hi> in the 3d. <hi>verſ.</hi> which <hi>Rulers</hi> are called in the ſame verſe the <hi>Powers.</hi> Beſides Power and Authority abſtracted from the Perſons in whom it is, cannot be ſaid to do what the <hi>Power</hi> or <hi>Powers,</hi> are ſaid to do, <hi>viz.</hi> to commend, or encourage, aveng or puniſh. Add to this, that the Apoſtle having mentioned the <hi>Power, verſ.</hi> the 3. and the <hi>Praiſe</hi> which they that do well have from it, he adds immediately, <hi>verſ.</hi> the 4th. <hi>For he</hi> (that muſt needs be the Perſon in Power) <hi>is the Miniſter of God to thee for good, and he bears not the Sword in vain,</hi> &amp;c. Nor can we think this uſe of the word ſtrange, becauſe 'tis thus uſed more than once in
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:64363:7"/>the Holy Scriptures, (See <hi>Luke</hi> 12. <hi>verſ.</hi> 11. and <hi>Chapter</hi> 8. of this Epiſtle, <hi>verſe</hi> 38. when the <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipality</hi> and <hi>Powers</hi> mentioned, are certainly the the Princes and Men in Power, which ſhould per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mute Chriſts Diſciples for their Faith) and becauſe 'tis thus uſed frequently in Human Authors, as might eaſily be ſhewed you, if I did think it neceſſary. And indeed Common Reaſon will teach us thus to interpret it; for Power ſeparated from the Perſon in whom it is, is but a <hi>Chimera</hi> or figment of the Brain, and ſerves to no purpoſe at all in the lives of men. In Notion (as we ſay) they are diſtinct, and may be conſidered aſſunder; but indeed they are one and the ſame and cannot poſſibly be divided. And therefore they that reſiſt the Perſons of them that are in Power, reſiſt their Power and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity too. The King of <hi>Syria</hi> that commanded his Captains, to ſight neither with ſmall nor great,<note place="margin">1 King. <hi>ult. v.</hi> 31. 2 Sam. 17.1, 2. 1 Sam. 24.4.</note> but againſt <hi>Ahab</hi> did bid them fight <hi>againſt the King of Iſrael.</hi> And <hi>Achitophels</hi> Counſel was not only a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>David,</hi> but againſt the King alſo. And when <hi>David</hi> cut off the Skirts of <hi>Saul</hi>'s Garment, his <hi>heart</hi> told him that he had injured the King, the <hi>Anointed of the Lord.</hi> To ſay that <hi>Ahab, Saul</hi> or <hi>David</hi> could be touched, wounded, ſlain, and their Power or Authority not violated, is to ſpeak ſuperfine, nice, (and to uſe the common phraſe of of ſome men) <hi>unſcriptural</hi> Nonſcence; to mince and diſtinguiſh things into juſt nothing; the Power and the Perſon in whom 'tis Seated being inſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. And this I have noted for the Condemnation of thoſe who were the Authors of that Diſtinction betwixt Power and Perſon, as if one might fight againſt the one, and not againſt the other;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:64363:8"/>And much more of thoſe who could not only di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh betwixt the Power and the Perſon, but could Arm the Authority or Power againſt the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that bare it. For ſo in the late damnable Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion; the <hi>Commons</hi> that raiſed it, did pretend the Kings Authority to take Arms againſt Himſelf; and though they took his Perſon Priſoner, and cut off his Head, yet they pretended that they did not deſign to hurt the King. A moſt Helliſh Device, and beyond any of old <hi>Achitophels,</hi> framed on purpoſe to overturn all ſetled Goverments, and to bring Confuſion and deſtruction upon all Human Society. Againſt which our Laws have ſince very well pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, requiring all perſons admitted to Offices and Places of truſt to abjure, or renounce upon Oath, the <hi>Trayterous poſition of taking Arms by the Kings Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority againſt his Perſon.</hi> Indeed 'tis hard to imagine that any rational People ſhould ever entertain ſuch a <hi>Trayterous Poſition;</hi> the Authority which is for the ſafety of Subjects being manifeſtly much more for the ſafety of the Sovereign. But what the Devil can do in the world (by Gods permiſſion) and what power he has over men, even wiſe men in wordly matters, that love not the Truth in ſincerity, but hold it in unrighteouſneſs is plain, as in other things, ſo in the prevalence of this ſence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Doctrine in the late Times, and by the backwardneſs of many to renounce it even in ours.</p>
            <p n="3">3. When the Apoſtle ſaith, that <hi>every Soul muſt be ſubject to the Higher Powers,</hi> we muſt not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it, as if he meant, that we muſt be ſubject to all the <hi>Powers</hi> that are in any part of the world, and may take upon them to command us; for
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:64363:8"/>what have we to do with the <hi>Powers</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> or <hi>Spain,</hi> or any other Countrey, and what have they to do with us: but we muſt underſtand it of our own <hi>Higher Powers, i. e.</hi> of thoſe whom God hath ſet over us, and are his <hi>Miniſters to us for our good.</hi> Other <hi>Powers</hi> have their people and ſubjects, and they, and their Bounds are known. They are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned only to command their own Subjects, and their Subjects are concerned to obey them only: And let them ſee to the Practiſe of their Duty: They have nothing to do with us, nor we with them, but as we have <hi>Powers</hi> or Governors of our own, ſo we muſt be ſubject to them, and them only. If therefore any Foreign Prince or Potentate ſhall take upon him to command us, we may, we muſt, ſlight his commands, and reſiſt his Forces, if he uſes any to compel us, that we may diſcharge or Duty to our own King and Governor. God has not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded us to <hi>Serve</hi> ſeveral <hi>Maſters</hi> of different in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt and deſigns, nay he has forbidden it, in that he has ſet <hi>One</hi> over us, and commanded us to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject unto him. And this is the more to be remembred by us, becauſe of the Popes claim, what Power and Authority not only over us, but over thoſe Powers alſo, which are ſet over us, by Almighty God. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Pope, and you muſt believe that we are his ſubjects, and that the King is ſo likewiſe, that he can depoſe him and give his Crown and Kingdom to another, if he ſees cauſe, that he can looſe the Bond of our Allegiance, and empower us to fight againſt him, and caſt him out of his Throne. This Power the Popes of <hi>Rome</hi> have claimed, but as we are ſure Chriſt never gave it them, ſo we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not own any ſuch Power in them but we muſt
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:64363:9"/>be guilty of the breach of our Duty towards the King. And againſt the owning of any ſuch Power, the <hi>Oath</hi> of <hi>Supremacy</hi> is a neceſſary and wiſe Caution.</p>
            <p n="4">4. By the <hi>Higher Powers</hi> we muſt underſtand not only the Higheſt <hi>Power</hi> in the Kingdom, <hi>i. e.</hi> the King, but the <hi>Powers,</hi> alſo that are ſubordinate to him, and commiſſionated by him. 'Tis not ſaid the <hi>Highest Power,</hi> or <hi>Higher Power,</hi> but the <hi>Higher Powers,</hi> 'Tis not to one only, but to many that we muſt be ſubject, but to thoſe many, not as <hi>Coordinate,</hi> for ſuch our Kingdom hath not, but as <hi>ſubordinate,</hi> as deriving Authority from one, <hi>i. e.</hi> the King, who is the <hi>Supreme,</hi> or the <hi>Higheſt Power,</hi> in the Kingdom. And thus St. <hi>Peter</hi> may expound St. <hi>Pauls</hi> meaning, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13. where both theſe are expreſt, and we are told, that we muſt <hi>Submit</hi> to the <hi>King,</hi> as <hi>Supreme</hi> in his Kingdom, and to <hi>Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors,</hi> as <hi>appointed by him.</hi> Which, as <hi>Beza</hi> notes, is added to prevent the cavil of thoſe who pretend obedience to the <hi>Supreme</hi> Magiſtrates, but deſpiſe his Officers, and Miniſters. And indeed Subjection to the Supream Magiſtrate carries this in it; Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty being derived from him, as the Head to them, as his Hands and Inſtruments. Do men expect that the King ſhould come to every one of them, and deliver his will and pleaſure to them in his own perſon? do they think that he Himſelf can do e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing that is to be done for the welfare of his Kingdom? Surely not. He muſt make uſe of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in moſt things, and do great part of his work by them; and as he muſt do this; ſo what we do to them is done as to himſelf; if we be ſubject to them acting by Authority from him, we are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:64363:9"/>to him; if we reſiſt them we reſiſt him. And this directly oppoſes that <hi>Traiterous</hi> Poſition of ſome in theſe Kingdoms. <hi>That though it be unlawful to take Arms againſt the King, yet it is lawful to take Arms againſt thoſe that are Commiſſionated by him.</hi> But againſt whom do they oppoſe themſelves when they oppoſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves againſt the Kings Commiſſioners? do they not oppoſe thoſe that Act by his Authority? And can they be reſiſted, and he not be reſiſted, his Autority not vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated? This is as much as to ſay, I ſtrike at a mans Legs or Arms, but not at the man, as if the man and his Legs or Arms were not all one, as if thoſe might be wounded, or cut off, and the man not hurt.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Though we muſt not underſtand by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles words, that it is our duty to be ſubject to the <hi>Higheſt Power</hi> only, yet we muſt underſtand them thus, that it is our Duty to be ſubject in the firſt place to the Higheſt, for here is an <hi>Emphaſis</hi> on the word <hi>Higher,</hi> and the <hi>Higher,</hi> is to be looked upon as the <hi>Power.</hi> 'Tis true, the Kings Miniſters are higher then we, and therefore we are to be ſubject to them (as has been ſaid) but the King is higher then they, and they, as we, are to be ſubject to him. The Power they have is the Kings, and they have no power againſt him, and therefore as long as they act un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the King and by his Authority, ſo long we are bound to he ſubject to them, but no longer. And by this we may know what we are to do, in caſe it ſhould happen that the inferior Magiſtrates or <hi>Powers</hi> ſhould divide from, and oppoſe themſelves, againſt the King, and require our Aſſiſtance. That we are to look upon the <hi>Higher</hi> as the <hi>Power,</hi> and to be ſubject to him; If, as in old Time, the <hi>Barons</hi> or any of the great Ones of the Kingdom ſhould call
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:64363:10"/>you to joyn with them, as being the <hi>Powers</hi> to whom you ought to be ſubject; you are to conſider who is higher, the Baron, or he that made him ſo. If any Parliament ſhould (as once you know a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament did) reſiſt the King, and require your Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance againſt him, as having Power, or being the <hi>Powers;</hi> you are to conſider who is the <hi>Higheſt Power:</hi> who called them or made them to be a Parliament? was it not the King by his Authority? who Eſtabliſheth all their Acts, and giveth them the force of Laws? Is it not the King? who is it that can diſſolve them and make them nothing? Is it not the King? He therefore is to be looked upon as the <hi>Higher Power,</hi> to whom we are to be ſubject.</p>
            <p n="6">6. When the Apoſtle requires every <hi>Soul to be Subject</hi> to the <hi>Higher Powers,</hi> you muſt underſtand him, of thoſe <hi>Powers</hi> that are lawfully and by true Right ſuch, and not by Uſurpation. An Uſurper can no more be ſaid to be the <hi>Higher Power,</hi> then one that drives thee out of thy houſe can be ſaid to be the true Owner of it. They only can be ſaid to be the <hi>Higher Powers,</hi> whoſe right it is to be ſo. And this, the word which is rendred <hi>Powers</hi> doth import, as every one knows that underſtands the Greek Tongue, and the words of the Apoſtle in the later part of this verſe ſhew us, that we muſt underſtand him thus, the <hi>Powers</hi> that we muſt be ſubject to, being ſuch, as <hi>are of God,</hi> and <hi>ordained of God,</hi> and <hi>the Miniſters of God:</hi> Not every one that can get into the Throne, by any means or Methods, is to be owned for our Sovereign, but He whoſe right it is to be in the Throne. And I need not ſay, that our preſent Sovereign has apparently that Right; becauſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the Crown's coming to him by a long lawful
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:64363:10"/>lineal Deſcent, His Right thereunto has been publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly owned by the three Eſtates of the Kingdom, Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled in Parliament; every Kingdom ſhould be to their King as <hi>Bucephalus</hi> is ſaid to have been to <hi>Alexander,</hi> he would carry none but his own Maſter; ſo a Kingdom ſhould bear none but its own law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful King and Governor. Every one that attempts the Throne ſhould be repelled, and he that uſurps it ſhould be caſt and thrown. There ſhould be <hi>overturning, overturning, overturning</hi> until he comes to take poſſeſſion, whoſe <hi>Right it is,</hi> as it was in the late times of Uſurpation and Tyranny. The King therefore, our preſent King, (for whoſe preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and protection we do dayly pray) and thoſe that are in Authority under him, are the <hi>Higher Powers</hi> whom the Apoſtle enjoyns us to be ſubject to; But,</p>
            <p n="7">7. You muſt note, that the Apoſtle does not ſay, that we muſt be ſubject to the <hi>Higher Powers</hi> if they be ſo and ſo qualified, if they be of this or that Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; but without any ſuch limitation, <hi>Let every Soul be ſubject to the Higher Powers.</hi> Now when the Law diſtinguiſhes not, it is not for us to do it, where God puts no limitation nor exception we ought not. It is a good note of <hi>Beta's</hi> upon the words, that the Apoſtle did not uſe <hi>a Trope here, putting the word Powers for them that have the Power raſhly and unad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſedly; but that we might know that it is our duty to be ſubject to them that are in Authority and Power, how unworthy ſoever they may ſeem to us to be of that Power and Authority.</hi> And Surely if ever any Perſon was unworthy of Power, <hi>Nero,</hi> who was Roman Emperour when this Epiſtle was written, was unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of it, for by the conſent of all Writers, he was a meer Monſter, a moſt filthy and cruel Tyrant;
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:64363:11"/>and yet the Apoſtle charged Chriſtians to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to him. And this Obſervation I have made, becauſe at this time ſome ignorant people, or worſe then ignorant, ſeem to think, That we are not bound to be ſubject to our preſent King, becauſe (as they ſay, ſpeaking what they know not) he is not of our Religion. But I beſeech you, <hi>Brethren,</hi> to conſider that <hi>Nero</hi> and thoſe that were in Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority under him were ſo far from being of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion, that they were bloudy perſecutors of it; and yet it was the Duty of Chriſtians then to be ſubject to them, and they were ſo really and heartily. And is it not our Duty to be ſubject to a Chriſtian Prince, for ſo our King is, to a Prince that is ſo far from perſecuting us for Religion, that he protects and defends both us, and it, and hath ſolemnly promiſed ſo to do; certainly it is. And if we think not ſo, I am ſure, we underſtand not the Religion of Chriſt, and do but ill deſerve that he ſhould protect either us, or that which we call our Religion, you ſee then who are the <hi>Higher Powers,</hi> whom we are to be ſubject to. Let us now</p>
            <p n="2">II. Conſider what it is to <hi>be ſubject</hi> to them. <hi>Let eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Soul be ſubject</hi> or <hi>let every Soul ſubject himſelf</hi> to the Higher Powers; for ſo the words may be rendred, we ſhould ſubject our ſelves to the Higher Powers, and not be forced to it by them: the more free and ready our ſubjection is, the more acceptable it is to God and them, but letting this paſs at preſent, the words, are not a permiſſion barely as of a thing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different, nor Counſel meerly as of a thing expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent; but <hi>Imperative</hi> of a thing that is our Duty. And therefore you may obſerve that the Apoſtle ſays afterwards, <hi>v.</hi> 5. <hi>wherefore</hi> we muſt <hi>needs be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject,</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:64363:11"/>there is a neceſſity laid upon us, we are under a Comamnd and an Indiſpenſible obligation to be ſo, <hi>not only for wrath, but ſor Conſcience ſake.</hi> Now the word, which we tranſlate, <hi>to be ſubject,</hi> ſeems to me to be of large ſignification, and to compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend our whole Duty to the <hi>Higher Powers,</hi> all that we are obliged to, as Inferiors or Subjects in our ſeveral ſtations or places, with reſpect to them, the ſeveral parts or branches whereof we are taught in other Texts of Scripture. I cannot but think it meet to mention briefly ſome of the cheifeſt.</p>
            <p n="1">1. There muſt be a ſubjection of the ſoul to them ſo far as to entertain a reverent eſteem of them, and to do our Duty as Subjects readily and faithfully, we muſt Reverence them for the place they are in, and the Authority they are Inverted with, as having Gods Authority, and his Sword of Juſtice, and Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance for the <hi>puniſhment of evil doers</hi> and <hi>the praiſe of them that do well,</hi> we are charged by <hi>Solomon</hi> to <hi>fear the Lord and the King,</hi> Prov. 24.21. Not the Lord only, but the King alſo. Now as the <hi>Fear of the Lord</hi> is nothing elſe but ſuch an awful ſence of his glorious Majeſty and Power, as ſubjects our whole man to his Will and Commandments; ſo the <hi>Fear</hi> of <hi>the</hi> King is nothing elſe but ſuch an inward Reverent eſteem of his Place, Dignity and Authority, as makes us to ſubject our ſelves unto him in all things that are not contrary to the will of God. Again, the ſame <hi>Solomon</hi> commands us <hi>not to curſe the King, no not in our thoughts,</hi> Eccl. 10.20. <hi>i. e.</hi> to entertain no mean and contemptuous thoughts of him, but to think as honourably of him as is poſſible, as of a Perſon whom Almighty God, whoſe wiſdom is greater than thine or mine, hath thought good to ſet over us, and to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:64363:12"/>next to himſelf in Power and Dignity. And this inward eſteem of the <hi>Higher Powers</hi> is the Soul and Life of that <hi>Honour,</hi> which the fifth Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment enjoyns us towards them; without which our outward Subjection is but little worth in the ſight of God, as proceeding not from Conſcience, but from force or fear of Puniſhment, and will as ſoon fail as that ſhall be removed, They are therefore wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men, who though they yeild outward Subjection to the Higher Powers, do yet in their hearts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temn them. Theſe are not Chriſts Diſciples, but Pope <hi>Hildebrands</hi> (or <hi>Gregory</hi> the Seventh) whoſe Doctrine it was, that <hi>Kings had their beginning from men, who affected Rule by the inſtigation of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. There muſt be a Subjection of the Tongue to the Higher Powers, <hi>i. e.</hi> we muſt uſe our Tongues to their honour, to expreſs and manifeſt the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence of our hearts towards them. When Saint <hi>Paul</hi> was to ſpeak for himſelf before King <hi>Agrippa</hi> and <hi>Feſtus,</hi> he gave <hi>Agrippa</hi> frequently the Title of King; and though <hi>Feſtus</hi> told him that he <hi>was beſide himſelf,</hi> (which was enough to have ſtirred an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Patience) he gave him a modeſt, a ſober Anſwer, with the Title of <hi>moſt noble Feſtus.</hi> Act. 26.25. And of the ſame Saint <hi>Paul</hi> we read, <hi>Act.</hi> 23.5. that when he had unadviſedly called the High Prieſt a <hi>Whited-wall,</hi> (being moved by a blow moſt unjuſtly given him,) and was reprehended for it, he acknowledged his fault, ſhewing how we ought to ſpeak to our Rulers by quoting a known Text of Scripture, <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſpeak evil of the Ruler of thy People.</hi> Which paſſage is the more to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred, becauſe it ſhews that it is not unlawful
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:64363:12"/>only to uſe unjuſt Reproaches, but even to ſpeak re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proachfully of the real Failings of our Governors: It being unqueſtionable, that the High Prieſt was no better than a <hi>Whited-wall,</hi> who pretending to judge according to the Law, did contrary to the Law, command an innocent Perſon to be ſmitten. We muſt therefore either not ſpeak at all of the <hi>Higher Powers,</hi> or elſe ſpeak well and honorably of them. We are too bold when we make them the Subjects of our common Diſcourſes, too ſawcy when we pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to cenſure their Actions, and we take too much upon us, when we pretend to fathom the Depth of their Policys, and to condemn the wiſdom of their proceedings. No Maſter will endure ſuch Behaviour from his Servants, no Parent from his Children: And yet every ordinary Peaſant, every rude and thick-ſculled <hi>Mechanic</hi> will be <hi>Prating</hi> of the Higher Powers, and calling them to their <hi>Bar,</hi> as if they thought themſelves able to teach them, how to govern the Kingdom. In this it is that Rebellion begins, when once men become ſo bold as to ſhoot the <hi>ſharp Arrows</hi> of their Tongues againſt their Governors, they uſually proceed to take Arms into their hands. Theſe <hi>unruly Talkers</hi> do more againſt the <hi>Powers</hi> then the Angels of God dare to do: and if you have any regard to what St. <hi>Peter</hi> and St. <hi>Jude</hi> have written, you muſt place them in the ſame Rank with the <hi>Apoſtate</hi> Spirits, and the <hi>filthy Sodomites,</hi> ſee the 2d. Epiſtle of St. <hi>Peter.</hi> Cap. 2. and read the Epiſtle of St. <hi>Jude.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Every Soul muſt be Obedient to the Higher Powers. <hi>Put them in mind</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Titus</hi> Cap. 3. v. 1.) to be <hi>Subject to Principalities and Powers, to obey Magiſtrates;</hi> we muſt obey all their
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:64363:13"/>juſt Laws, all their lawful Commands, <hi>i.e.</hi> What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they require and enjoyn, if we can do it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſinning againſt God (whoſe Power is greater than theirs) we muſt do it. I ſay we muſt do it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe when the Laws may be obeyed without ſin, our diſobedience is a ſin, and our ſuffering the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty doth not remove the ſin, nor free us from the Judgment of God. And this I have ſaid, to ſhew you the ill uſe that is commonly made of a Diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on currant among us, of <hi>Active</hi> and <hi>Paſſive</hi> Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, as if men might break the juſt Laws of the King, and yet be good Subjects, and not break this Commandment of God; becauſe they ſuffer the penalty, when they cannot avoid it. And ſo by the help of this Diſtinction (which is none of the beſt) thoſe that leaſt reſpect Authority, would be thought as Dutiful and Obedient Subjects, as they that are moſt obſervant of the Laws. But as Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God the Supreme Ruler and Governor of the World, when he gave Laws to mankind, did not intend that they ſhould break them and dye; ſo the <hi>Powers</hi> that he hath ſet over us, have not made Laws that men may be puniſhed for breaking them, but that they may obſerve them for their own and the publick Good. And unleſs it be equally good to the King, that his Subjects obey or be puniſhed; unleſs it be all one to him whether they be bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitted by the Laws, or made miſerable, it cannot be thought that the Law is ſatisfied in its main Intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, when the Subject is puniſhed for the breach of it. It is very true, that when any Law is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to any Command of God, Subjects are not bound to <hi>Active</hi> obedience, for <hi>God muſt be obeyed rather than men;</hi> and then the <hi>Paſſive</hi> Obedience or
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:64363:13"/>Submiſſion to the Puniſhment is <hi>Sufficient;</hi> but when the Law of the King is not contrary to any Command of God, the chuſing of <hi>Paſſive</hi> Obedience before <hi>Active</hi> is a real Contempt and Scandal.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Our Purſes and Eſtates muſt be ſo far ſubject to the <hi>Higher Powers,</hi> as the paying of Taxes, Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes and Cuſtoms according as the Laws do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire. When the Queſtion was propoſed to our bleſſed Saviour by ſome <hi>Jews,</hi> whether it were law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to pay Tribute to <hi>Caeſar</hi> or not? He anſwered, <hi>Render unto Caeſar the things that are Caeſars,</hi> Math. 22.21. Cuſtoms and Tributes are <hi>Caeſars,</hi> therefore <hi>Caeſar</hi> muſt have them. And the Apoſtle here men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions it as an Inſtance of our ſubjection to the <hi>Higher Powers.</hi> That we pay them Tribute, <hi>verſ.</hi> 7. <hi>Render to all their Dues, Tribute to whom Tribute is due, Cuſtom to whom Cuſtom.</hi> And due they are to the <hi>Higher Powers,</hi> both in Juſtice and Gratitude, for they are at the coſt of our Defence and Protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the Benefits we partake of by their care and pains are innumerable and invaluable. They are <hi>Gods Miniſters attending continually upon this very thing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. We ought to be ſubject in undertaking ſuch Offices as the <hi>Higher Powers</hi> ſhall call us to, and in diſcharging them faithfully for their honour and the publick good. Kings cannot do all things them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, in their own Perſons, but muſt make uſe of others in ſeveral employments, and who can they better make uſe of then their own ſubjects, and who are obliged to undertake them but they: To thoſe offices or employments that are mean and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:64363:14"/>inferior the Dignity of Kings is not to condeſcend; in thoſe that are dangerous, the ſafety of their Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons is not to be hazarded. The People of <hi>Iſrael</hi> would not conſent that <hi>David</hi> their King ſhould go out with them to Battle, for fear of <hi>quenching their light,</hi> and they looked upon him as <hi>worth many Thouſands of them.</hi> The People are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> they are to aſſiſt their Prince with their bodys and their Purſes in the ſervice of War.</p>
            <p n="6">6. We muſt be ſo ſubject to all their cenſures and puniſhments, as in no caſe to reſiſt them. If they lay heavy burdens upon us, oppreſs and wrong us, yea perſecute us even to death, we muſt not tumultuate and rebel againſt them. <hi>There is no Power</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle here) <hi>but is of God, and the Powers that be are ordained of God.</hi> They have their Authority from God and not from us, and they are over us by Gods appointment, as his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters; and though God gave them their Power for their ſubjects good, yet if they will abuſe it, they are reſponſible to God for it, and not to us, he has Power to puniſh them, but we have none, and he will do it when, and in what manner, he ſees good; and it is better for us to leave him to do it who hath ſaid <hi>Vengeance is mine,</hi> and I <hi>will repay,</hi> then to take upon us to do it our ſelves; and if we do ſo, we are ſure of a ſufficient reward for our patient ſubmiſſion; but if we <hi>reſiſt them,</hi> the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle tells us, <hi>we reſiſt the Ordinance of God,</hi> we are Rebellious not only againſt our King, but againſt God himſelf, and therefore our reſiſtance is highly finful and damnable; for <hi>They that reſiſt ſhall receive to themſelves Damnation.</hi> To which let me add the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:64363:14"/>words of St. <hi>Peter</hi> 1 <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 2.20. Where reſiſtance is plainly forbidden even to an innocent Perſon. <hi>For what glory is it, if when ye be buffeted for your Faults, ye ſhall take it patiently; but if when ye do well and ſuffer for it, ye ſhall take it patiently, this is accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table with God, for even hereunto were ye called, becauſe Christ alſo ſuffered for us, leaving us an example that ye ſhould follow his ſteps, who did no ſin, neither was Guile found in his Mouth; who when he was reviled, reviled not again; when he ſuffered, he threatned not, but committed himſelf</hi> [or his cauſe] <hi>to him that judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth righteouſly.</hi> This Doctrine the Apoſtles of our Lord taught, and the example of their Lord and ours they followed, and ſo did all Chriſtians for above ſix hundred years after Chriſt, not only not Rebelling, or Caballing, or Conſpiring againſt the <hi>Higher Powers,</hi> when they were moſt of all tempted to it, when they were perſecuted and oppreſſed, kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and tormented, ſpoyled of their goods, and every way moſt diſpightfully uſed; but alſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing it to be unlawful. And therefore if any be not convinced, that this is their Duty; if any do believe, and will take upon them, to maintain that they may lawfully in any caſe, or for any cauſe, (ſuppoſe it be for Religion) Rebel againſt, or in any tumultuous and violent ways, reſiſt the Higher Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, they ought to be looked upon as wretched Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates from one of the moſt conſiderable points of the Chriſtian Doctrine; as the maintainers of one of the moſt pernicious and damnable Hereſies that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was brought into the world. Now in the practice of theſe Dutys does our ſubjection to the <hi>Higher Powers</hi> mainly conſiſt and ſhew it ſelf; and if we
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:64363:15"/>will obſerve this precept of the Apoſtle, it behoves us to take care that we be not wanting in any one of them.</p>
            <p n="3">III. I proceed now to ſhew you what is meant by <hi>every Soul,</hi> or who are the Perſons who are bound to be ſubject to the <hi>Higher Powers.</hi> Concerning which there is no doubt but by <hi>every Soul,</hi> the Apoſtle means every man by an uſual <hi>Synecdoche.</hi> It is poſſible indeed that the Apoſtle did make choice to ſpeak thus, putting the <hi>Soul</hi> for the man, to intimate that our ſubjection to the <hi>Higher Powers,</hi> ſhould be from the Heart and Soul, free, ready, cheerful; not by conſtraint which is bruitiſh; not meerly Paſſive, but in all lawful things Active, but it mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters not whether he did ſo or not, for it is evident enough from other places of Scripture, that it ought to be ſo; that which the Apoſtle teaches concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſubjection or obedience of Servants to their Maſters, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.6.7. and <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 3.23. being appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable with advantage to the ſubjection of all Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors to the Higher Powers. That which I think my ſelf concerned to note is, That all Perſons without exception of any, ought to be ſubject to the <hi>Higher Powers:</hi> Let <hi>every Soul</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion that includes all and excludes none. And thus any unprejudiced man of common fences one would think muſt underſtand it, for beſides the force of the expreſſion it ſelf, <hi>every Soul,</hi> the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles words afterwards, <hi>whoſoever reſiſteth the Powers — and they that reſiſt —and wilt thou not he afraid of the Power— And he is the Miniſter of God to thee,</hi> &amp;c. ſeem to be uſed on purpoſe to direct every one that is not a
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:64363:15"/>
               <hi>Higher Power,</hi> or <hi>Ruder,</hi> to take the precept as gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to himſelf. And yet notwithſtanding this the Popes of <hi>Rome</hi> and their Adherents for ſeveral hundreds of years have made bold ſo to diſtinguiſh and limit the Apoſtles words, as to exempt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and all their Clergy, from ſubjection to the <hi>Civil Powers.</hi> But what Warrant they have from God to do thus I am altogether ignorant. We know that our Bleſſed Saviour owned the Power of the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperor, and thoſe that were in Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority under him, and ſubmitted himſelf to it without pleading any exemption. For thus he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered <hi>Pilate</hi> when he ſpake to him of his Power, <hi>Thou couldeſt have no Power at all againſt me, except it were given thee from above</hi> Joh. 19.11. And we are ſure, that when the Apoſtles were brought before Principalities and <hi>Powers</hi> for their faith ſake, they never excepted againſt their Power, but defended themſelves and their Doctrine before them; yea St. <hi>Paul</hi> did plainly own their Authority, and it is written for our Inſtruction in this point Act. 25.10, 11. I <hi>ſtand</hi> (ſaith he) at <hi>Caeſars Judgment Seat, where I ought to be judged,</hi> [mark that] <hi>If I be an offender, or have committed any thing worthy of death, I refuſe not to dye, I appeal unto Caeſar.</hi> Which <hi>Appealing</hi> unto <hi>Caeſar</hi> was a plain owning of his Authority over him. For the Liberty of Appealing to the <hi>Roman</hi> Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror was a priviledge granted only to them that were free Citizens of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Apoſtle could not claim this but by owning himſelf a Citizen of <hi>Rome,</hi> and therefore a ſubject to the cheif Governor there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. It is no leſs certain that the Holy Fathers and Biſhops of the Church, yea and of <hi>Rome</hi> too, for
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:64363:16"/>above ſix hundreds years after Chriſt, did not only acknowledge themſelves ſubject to the Civil <hi>Powers,</hi> but did declare that they, and all men whatſoever, were bound to be ſo. St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> upon the Text ſays, that not only <hi>Seculars</hi> but <hi>Prieſts and Monks are to be ſubject,</hi> and <hi>although thou beeſt an Apoſtle, or an Evangeliſt, or a Prophet; for this obedience to be ſure will not deſtroy thy piety.</hi> And if we may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve a Biſhop of the Roman Church of late years, as we reaſonably may, other ancient Fathers as <hi>Euthymius, Theoderet, Theophylact,</hi> &amp;c. and all the Greek Doctors do agree with him. And <hi>Gregory,</hi> ſurnamed the Great, Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> doth ſo expound the Text. And Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> many years afterwards,) in his Epiſtle to a Biſhop ſaid thus. <hi>Every Soul</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>then muſt you also</hi> (speaking to the Bishop of <hi>Senona</hi>) <hi>be subject; who hath exempted you? He that doth offer to exempt you, doth but offer to deceive you.</hi> And therefore let not the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> boaſt of her ſincere delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to men the truly Ancient, Catholick, and Apoſtolick Doctrine: Let no <hi>Papiſt</hi> boaſt of their Loyal Principles or Practiſes, or charge any Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants with Seditions and Traiterous Doctrines; with diſloyal, Treaſonable, and Rebellious Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes, as confidently as if they themſelves were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent; for beſides what has now been diſcourſed, I doubt not to ſay, and do ſay it upon the Faith of a Chriſtian, That I know no Seditious or Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Principle, no Doctrines diſtructive to Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment entertained and aſſerted by any called Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, but the ſame have been aſſerted and taught by ſome Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> and their Adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:64363:16"/>But thanks be to God that the Church of <hi>England</hi> can be charged with no ſuch miſcheivous and damnable Doctrines; whoſe Doctrine I am ſure I have now taught you, and as I do ſtedfaſtly believe it to he the Doctrine of Chriſt and his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, ſo I doubt not, but by Gods Grace, I ſhall continue in the belief of it to the end of my Life. Thus have I explained the words of my Text, and I hope clearly and profitably with reſpect to the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy circumſtances that this Kingdom is at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent under.</p>
            <p>And now to conclude this Diſcourſe in as few words as may be. Not to trouble you with Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints of the little Sence which many men have of their Duty to the Higher Powers, which every wiſe and good man cannot but obſerve, and be ſadly and ſorrowfully affected with: Let me in ſhort propoſe ſome few Queſtions to you, and if it be poſſible, to oblige you thereby ſeriouſly to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what it is, that ſo indiſpoſes ſome (to uſe no harder a term) to honour, obey and ſerve our preſent Lord the King, that they can hardly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure to be told, that they ought to do ſo. Have any among you ſo little Knowledge of the Goſpel, after ſo many years enjoyment of it, as to think what has now been delivered to be no part of the Goſpel, which Chriſts Miniſters ought to Preach? Are you ſo little able to diſtinguiſh between true Chriſtian (<hi>Proteſtant</hi>) Doctrine and <hi>Popery,</hi> as to call the Preaching of Subjection to the Higher Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers Popery? have you had the Holy Scriptures ſo many years in your Hands, in your own Language, and pretended to make them, and them, only the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:64363:17"/>Rule of your Faith and Practiſe? and can you be ignorant of, or will you reject the truths now de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered out of them, and writted ſo plainly in them, that none but thoſe who will ſhut their eyes can avoid ſeeing them? Hath St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſo little credit with us, when he tells us, <hi>That there is no Power but of God, and the Powers that be are ordained of God,</hi> that we will not believe him? or can we poſſibly faſten any other ſence upon his words but this, that it is God that makes Kings, and not men; That whatever they are as to their Perſonal Qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Abilitys for Government, or Religion, they have their Authority from God, and are his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters? And if this be his meaning, have we not good reaſon to believe, that if we diſpiſe them, we deſpiſe God; if we reproach and ſpeak evil of them, we reproach and blaſpheme God; if we diſobey their juſt Laws, we diſobey God; if we murmur, reſiſt, rebel againſt the King, we murmur and rebel againſt God. And can we think, that they can eſcape the Judgment of God, who do ſo? Can we have ſuch thoughts of God, as to imagine, that he is not concerned in a ſpecial manner for the ſafety, the Rights and Intereſts of his own Vicegerents; and the Defence and Maintenance of his own Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in them for the Government of the world? Are we yet to learn what the miſerable Ends of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious, trayterous and Rebellious Perſons uſually are? Has Liberty, Peace and Plenty made us ſo wanton (for I am ſure we yet have ſuffered no Oppreſſion to make us mad, nor any want but what our own Prodigality, idleneſs and viciouſneſs have brought upon us) that we care not what we do to bring
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:64363:17"/>confuſion upon us? Are we ſuch Sots and Fools as to liſten to the curſed whiſperings of every <hi>Achito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phel,</hi> and to dance after the Pipe of every <hi>Shebah,</hi> that ſhall be ſo mad as to blow a Trumpet in Iſrael, and ſay, <hi>we have no part in David, nor Inheritance in the Son of Jeſſe?</hi> Can we propoſe any thing ſo good to our ſelves by overturning the, Preſent Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as to reſolve to endure all the miſeries of War, and to march through a Sea of Blood for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſing of it? Are not all our Intereſts more ſafe and ſecure in the boſom of the Divine Providence whilſt we continue quiet in our ſeveral Places, and <hi>ſtudy to do our own Buſineſs,</hi> then they would be under the Shields and Bucklers of the moſt famous Warriors, in the ways of Treaſon and Rebellion? Is the Author and Protector of our moſt holy Religion become ſo careleſs of it, or ſo weak and feeble, that we muſt needs ſly to the Devil to ſupport it? ſhall we turn the Religion of the <hi>Croſs</hi> in to a Religion of the <hi>Sword,</hi> and change our <hi>Bibles</hi> for the <hi>Alchoran?</hi> Were all the holy men of old, who could not fight for their Religion, even when they might have overcome (ſo great were their numbers and their Reſolution) but could dye for it, ſuch fools, that we think it madneſs to follow their Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample? Have we been reproaching the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> for ſo many years, (and that juſtly) with their Trayterous and Rebellious Principles and Practiſes, and ſhall we now <hi>lick,</hi> up their <hi>Vomit,</hi> and juſtify all their Treaſons and Rebellions by treading in their ſteps? Is it the way to render our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion lovely in the eyes of the world, and to endear to it our Governors, to do thus? And can we hope
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:64363:18"/>to engage Almighty God to take care of its preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation by the worſt practiſes we dare be Guilty of againſt his Vicegerent? In one word, can we take it to be the way to Heaven, to break the Order of the Divine Providence in the Government of the World, to ſet at naught ſo many plain and expreſs Commands from Chriſt, and diſpiſing all the Bleſſings of Peace to endeavour all the ways we can after confuſion and deſtruction: we cannot ſurely be ſo unreaſonable.</p>
            <p>Let us therefore, I beſeech you, ſhew our ſelves Men and Chriſtians, Chriſtians of the Communion of the beſt Church in the World, a Church <hi>built upon a Rock,</hi> that can never fall, if we do not overthrow it our ſelves, by our abuſe of the Goſpel, and all thoſe Excellent means of Piety and Vertue which we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of in it. Let us <hi>fear the Lord, and the King, and not meddle with them that are given to change;</hi> And being ſtedfaſtly perſwaded, that Almighty God is King over all, that <hi>He ſtandeth in the Congregation of the Mighty, and is Judg among the Gods;</hi> that he will not only execute Judgment in another world, but doth Govern this, and conſequently will ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Protect us from Violence and Perſecution, or crown our Patience and avenge our Cauſe; let us always ſhew our ſelves good Chriſtians by being Loyal Subjects: And to the conſtant Practiſe of all that hath been now taught, let us add our dayly Prayers to God in the behalf of our preſent <hi>Sovereign, That it may pleaſe God ſo to bleſs and preſerve him, that he may rule over us many years in the Fear of God, the conſtant exerciſe of Piety, Juſtice and Mercy, and in Proſperity and Peace: That he may continue to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:64363:18"/>the Hearts of all his Subjects, and ever have them: That he may never give them any just cause for Jealousys and Suſpicions, and they never entertain any without Cauſe: That he may be happy by our conſtant Practiſe of true Chriſtian Loyalty, and we be ſo likewiſe by his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant and effectual Care to maintain and promote the true Profeſſion and Practiſe of Religion, and the welfare of the Church of God.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
